<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Perl | Blog 1]]></title>
  <link href="https://vincenttam.github.io/blog/categories/perl/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://vincenttam.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-04-17T18:11:46+08:00</updated>
  <id>https://vincenttam.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vincent Tam]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Loop Through an Array Having Only One Element in Bash]]></title>
      <link href="https://vincenttam.github.io/blog/2016/04/08/loop-through-an-array-having-only-one-element-in-bash/"/>
    
    <updated>2016-04-08T22:59:29+08:00</updated>
    <id>https://vincenttam.github.io/blog/2016/04/08/loop-through-an-array-having-only-one-element-in-bash</id>
    
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="background">Background</h2>

<p>To find out a way to loop through all elements in an array consisting
of more than one element, it’s easy.</p>

<pre class="cliUB"><code>$ for f in {"hello","world"}; do echo $f; done
hello
world
</code></pre>

<h2 id="problem">Problem</h2>

<p>When I try to take away the second element in the above array so that
it becomes an array consisting in <em>one</em> single element, then I get
<code>{hello}</code> instead of <code>hello</code>.</p>

<pre class="cliUB"><code>$ for f in {"hello"}; do echo $f; done
{hello}
</code></pre>

<p><strong>How can one get back an output consistent with the case of arrays
consisting of multiple elements?</strong></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="motivation">Motivation</h2>

<p>This problem seems nonsense–loops are supposed to do repetitive
tasks.  If the loop has <em>only</em> one iteration, then we can directly
type in the command, instead of adapting it into a loop and setting up
the scope of the loop.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, if one converts multiple lines of short texts into one
long single line with <code>xargs</code>, then the items will be separated by
white spaces.  This <em>won’t</em> work with the above for loop.  To change
the delimiter from white space to comma, one may use <code>paste -d, -s</code>.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: left">Syntax</th>
      <th style="text-align: left">Meaning</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left"><code>-d,</code></td>
      <td style="text-align: left">Use <code>,</code> as the delimiter.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left"><code>-s</code></td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><em>Without</em> this flag, <code>$1</code> and <code>$2</code> are displayed in <em>parallel</em>.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Surely, there are other tools to do this, such as <code>sed</code>.  However, I
think that <code>paste -d, -s</code> should be the <em>simplest</em> way to do this.
Note that the white space character between the two flags are
<em>important</em>.  Otherwise, this command <em>won’t</em> work.</p>

<p><em>Without</em> prior knowledge of the text to be processed, it’s possible
that the output of <code>paste -d, -s</code> consists of <em>only</em> one item.  This
single case is easy to deal with, even though the handling may be a
bit different from the case of multiple elements.  However, if the
syntax for the command that handles the output of <code>paste -d, -s</code>
<em>isn’t exactly the same</em> in the case of <em>one</em> single element and the
case of <em>multiple</em> elements, then we need to look at the content and
make manual judgement–this is tedious and error-prone.</p>

<p>In the problem posed in the previous section, if the list in the
for loop has <em>only</em> one item, then we need to do something different
from a list having two or more items.  If we observe this difference
with our naked eyes, the whole process will lack efficiency.</p>

<p>To solve this problem, we seek an <em>unified</em> approach.  In other words,
I try to change the syntax of the above for loop so that the for loop
will work for <em>any</em> one of these two cases.</p>

<h2 id="solution">Solution</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Surround each string in the array by a pair of <em>double quotes</em>.</li>
  <li>Add a comma <em>either</em> before the first element or after the last
element.</li>
</ol>

<p>The first step is needed if in the array, there exists an element
having two or more words <em>separated by a white space</em>; the second step
is needed for an array with one single element.</p>

<pre class="cliUB"><code>$ for f in {"hello world",}; do echo $f; done
hello world
</code></pre>

<h2 id="remarks">Remarks</h2>

<p>As the number of steps increases, the difficulty of constructing a
one-line command to do the thing rises tremendously.  It’s possible
that a shell script is <em>easier</em> to write.  By searching “bash array
tutorial” on Google, I got <a href="http://www.thegeekstuff.com/2010/06/bash-array-tutorial/">a tutorial on the Geek Stuff</a> in the
first search result.</p>

<p><figure class='code'><figcaption><span>A shell script that display an array (oneelt.sh)</span> <a href='/downloads/code/oneelt.sh'>download</a></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'><span class="c">#!/bin/bash</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nv">arr</span><span class="o">=(</span><span class="s2">&quot;hello&quot;</span><span class="o">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">for</span> f in <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">arr</span><span class="p">[@]</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="k">do</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="nv">$f</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">done</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></p>

]]></content>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oneline Perl]]></title>
      <link href="https://vincenttam.github.io/blog/2016/04/04/oneline-perl/"/>
    
    <updated>2016-04-04T00:47:40+08:00</updated>
    <id>https://vincenttam.github.io/blog/2016/04/04/oneline-perl</id>
    
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="motivation">Motivation</h2>

<p>Knowing some regular expressions in Vim, I hope to apply these
concepts to Perl so that I can search and replace some simple strings
directly in base <em>without</em> having to open the editor.</p>

<p>As a Vim user, the class of special characters in Perl is more
<em>natural</em> than that of <code>sed</code>.</p>

<h2 id="problem">Problem</h2>

<p>In <a href="/blog/2016/04/03/searching-git-commit-messages/">the previous post</a>, the list of Git commit messages containing
the string “HTTPS” is the main focus.  However, the alignment of this
list <em>isn’t</em> good: in the column representing the day, the data can be
either one or two digit.  Though I can still extract information with
<code>awk '{print $[col_num]}'</code>, it’s better to fix the alignment.</p>

<pre class="cliUB"><code>$ git log -2 --grep="HTTPS" --pretty="%h %cd %s"
7400582 Sun Mar 20 20:19:47 2016 +0800 Updated my Rakefile with HTTPS
b6f4f1f Mon Feb 8 00:45:02 2016 +0800 A new article about Flair, Octopress and HTTPS
</code></pre>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="start-using-perl">Start using Perl</h2>

<p>Searching “perl intro” online, one can easily find some basic Perl
scripts.  I tried to issue some simple one-line Perl command to save
time, but I <em>couldn’t</em> easily find them.  Thanks to
<a href="http://articles.mongueurs.net/magazines/linuxmag50.html">a webpage by Philippe Bruhat</a>, I managed to starting using
Perl.  I jot them down here.</p>

<pre class="cliUB"><code>$ perl -e 'print "hello \n"'  # single quote outside
hello
$ perl -e "\$str='abc'; print \$str;"  # escape $, no EOL
abc
$ perl -e "$str='test'; print $str.'\n';"  # not desired
test\n
$ perl -e '$str="test"; print $str."\n";'  # want newlne
test
</code></pre>

<p>The <code>-e</code> flag above stands for “execute”.</p>

<h2 id="read-from-external-command">Read from external command</h2>

<p>Unluckily, I <em>didn’t</em> know how to use <code>system()</code> nor backticks to pass
output of a command into Perl.  After trying a few search keywords,
“perl oneline read command output” worked best for me.  It was quite
<em>uncommon</em> that I found the <em>eighth</em> result useful.  In the article
<a href="http://www.theperlreview.com/articles/one-liners.html"><em>Perl One-liners</em></a>, I found out the answer.</p>

<pre class="cliUB"><code>$ for (( i = 1; i &lt;= 10; i++ )); do
  echo $i
  done | perl -e 'while (&lt;&gt;) {s/(?&lt;!\d)\d{1}(?!\d)/0$&amp;/; print $_}'
01
02
03
04
05
06
07
08
09
10
</code></pre>

<p>In fact, the flag <code>-n</code> can be used to replace the <code>while (&lt;&gt;) {...}</code>
loop.  The <code>-p</code> flag has the function of <code>-n</code> but <em>also</em> prints the
output.  I learnt them from <a href="https://www.kernel.org/pub/software/scm/git/docs/git-log.html">Git manual web page for git-log</a>.</p>

<h2 id="solution">Solution</h2>

<p>Combine the above observations together.</p>

<pre class="cliUB"><code>$ git log -2 --grep="HTTPS" --pretty="%h %cd %s" \
  | perl -pe 's/(?&lt;=\u\l\l )\d{1}(?= )/0$&amp;/'
7400582 Sun Mar 20 20:19:47 2016 +0800 Updated my Rakefile with HTTPS
b6f4f1f Mon Feb 08 00:45:02 2016 +0800 A new article about Flair, Octopress and 
HTTPS
</code></pre>

<h2 id="lessons-learnt">Lessons learnt</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Perl: Apart from the above syntax, I’ve also learnt to use <code>$&amp;</code> and
<code>\b</code> in the replacement.  This is the Perl counterpart of <code>&amp;</code> and
<code>\&lt;</code> or <code>\&gt;</code> in Vim respectively.</li>
  <li>Git: In <code>git log</code> and <code>git show</code>,
    <ul>
      <li><code>--name-only</code>: suppress the diff hunk</li>
      <li><code>--pretty=format:</code> display nothing</li>
      <li><code>format</code> vs <code>tformat</code>: <code>t</code> stands for “terminator” (a.k.a. EOL)</li>
    </ul>

    <p>Each of each flags seems to be useless.  Nevertheless, <em>when
 combined together</em>, they help extract the edited files in a
 particular commit.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Posting long commands in a blog entry</p>

    <p>From the two codeblocks explaining the difference between <code>format</code>
 and <code>tformat</code> in the Git manual, I understand that it’s better to
 end each line with a backslash, then continue with the command.
 In bash,  a <code>&gt;</code> is then automatically inserted at the beginning of
 each line.  This is carried from the shell to the source file of
 the blog article by copy and paste.  I used to think that it’s
 good to keep this so that this and the Ubuntu font will give a
 sense of reality to the reader.  However, this also causes
 inconvenience to those who want to try this command.  From now on,
 I <em>won’t</em> include this character anymore at the beginning of a
 long command exceeding 80 characters.  I will replace it with a
 white space instead.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

]]></content>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
