<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Hardware | Blog 1]]></title>
  <link href="http://vincenttam.github.io/blog/categories/hardware/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vincenttam.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-12T00:50:31+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://vincenttam.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vincent Tam]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Scanner and Ubuntu 14.04]]></title>
      <link href="http://vincenttam.github.io/blog/2014/08/14/my-scanner-and-ubuntu-14-dot-04/"/>
    
    <updated>2014-08-14T11:57:26+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://vincenttam.github.io/blog/2014/08/14/my-scanner-and-ubuntu-14-dot-04</id>
    
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="background">Background</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Scanning and printing works fine in my Ubuntu 12.04 desktop.</li>
  <li>I’ve upgraded to Ubuntu 14.04 LTS yesterday.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote">1</a></sup></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="problem">Problem</h2>

<p>When I used Simple Scan, Ubuntu’s GUI tool for scanning documents, I
encountered an error—the program <em>couldn’t</em> detect my scanner.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/Ubuntu1404Scan/ecscan.png" alt="Simple Scan didn't detect my scanner" /></p>

<p><strong>How can I scan images from my scanner in Ubuntu?</strong></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="discussion">Discussion</h2>

<p>The working principle GUI tools are <em>much</em> more complicated than its
command line counterpart.</p>

<p>I’ll illustrate the idea by a typical component in GUI by borrowing
other’s depication of the <em>delegation model</em> in Java GUI programming.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/Ubuntu1404Scan/AWT_ActionListener.png" alt="Java GUI button and listener" /><br />
<img src="/images/posts/Ubuntu1404Scan/AWT_WindowEventSeqDiagram.png" alt="Java GUI delegation model" /><br />
<small>Source: <em>yet another insignificant programming
notes</em><sup id="fnref:img_src"><a href="#fn:img_src" class="footnote">2</a></sup></small></p>

<p>In my opinion, the working principle of a button in GUI is much more
abstract than that of the nervous system in a human body.  One can
learn about the bilogical principles through observations of concrete
objects.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/Ubuntu1404Scan/VoluntaryAction.jpg" alt="Human nervous system" /><br />
<small>Source: <em>Passnownow</em><sup id="fnref:img_src2"><a href="#fn:img_src2" class="footnote">3</a></sup></small></p>

<h2 id="solution">Solution</h2>

<h3 id="temporary-method">Temporary method</h3>

<p>Therefore, I immediately googled the *nix command for scanning
documents, and came up with <code>brscan-skey</code>.  I ran it with the <code>-l</code>
flag, the it said that my scanner <em>wasn’t</em> registered.</p>

<pre class="cli"><code class="UBMono"># brscan-skey
# brscan-skey -l
 XXX-XXXX          : brotherX:busX;devX  : USB                  <span class="err">Not registered</span>
</code></pre>

<p>A <a href="http://ubuntuforums.org/showthread.php?t=937898&amp;p=11707315#post11707315" title="Re: Brother MFC-465CN">comment</a> for <em>Brother MFC-465CN</em> took me to Brother’s
documentation for Linux drivers, but finding the right page by viewing
the right hyperlink was too slow, so I searched the command and
restricted the results to those in Brother’s website.  The page in the
official documentation inspired me to add the following lines just
before the last line of <code>/lib/udev/rules.d/40-libsane.rules</code>.<sup id="fnref:doc"><a href="#fn:doc" class="footnote">4</a></sup></p>

<pre><code># Brother scanners
ATTRS{idVendor}=="04f9", ENV{libsane_matched}="yes"
</code></pre>

<p>I rebooted my computer and my scanner became “active”.  However,
Simple Scan still <em>couldn’t</em> detect it.  I followed the official
documentation and pressed “Scan” button on the device.  It worked and
the scanned files with the TIFF format could be found under
<code>~/brscan/</code>.</p>

<p>After an hour, when I ran the <em>same</em> command to list out the devices
that <code>brscan-skey</code> could detect, I got <em>no</em> output.</p>

<p>However, I could still use the button on my scanner to produce scanned
images.</p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">

      <p>Refer to <a href="/blog/2014/08/12/ubuntu-distribution-upgrade-to-14-dot-04/"><em>Ubuntu Distribution Upgrade to 14.04</em></a> and
<a href="/blog/2014/08/13/upgraded-ubuntu/"><em>Upgraded Ubuntu</em></a> for details. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:img_src">

      <p>Chua Hock-Chuan.  (2014, March).  <em>Java Programming Tutorial</em>.
Retrieved 12:25, August 14, 2014, from
<a href="http://www.ntu.edu.sg/home/ehchua/programming/java/j4a_gui.html#zz-3.1">http://www.ntu.edu.sg/home/ehchua/programming/java/j4a_gui.html#zz-3.1</a> <a href="#fnref:img_src" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:img_src2">

      <p>Reflex and Voluntary Actions.  (n.d.).  In <em>Passnownow</em>.
Retrieved 12:52, August 14, 2014, from
<a href="http://passnownow.com/classwork-series-and-exercises-biology-ss3-reflex-and-voluntary-actions/">http://passnownow.com/classwork-series-and-exercises-biology-ss3-reflex-and-voluntary-actions/</a> <a href="#fnref:img_src2" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:doc">

      <p>Scanner setting for normal user. (2013). In <em>Linux Informations</em>.
Retrieved 13:53, August 14, 2014, from
<a href="http://support.brother.com/g/s/id/linux/en/instruction_scn1c.html?c=us_ot&amp;lang=en&amp;redirect=on#u9.10">http://support.brother.com/g/s/id/linux/en/instruction_scn1c.html?c=us_ot&amp;lang=en&amp;redirect=on#u9.10</a> <a href="#fnref:doc" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Desktop Crashed!]]></title>
      <link href="http://vincenttam.github.io/blog/2014/05/27/my-desktop-crashed/"/>
    
    <updated>2014-05-27T00:22:22+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://vincenttam.github.io/blog/2014/05/27/my-desktop-crashed</id>
    
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="beginning">Beginning</h2>

<p>Last Saturday night, I used my Ubuntu Desktop to watch some videos.
While it was playing, the recently upgraded Firefox suddenly hanged.
The screen was freezed, and the sound continued to play.  To avoid
disturbing my neighbour, I muted the monitor speakers.  I initially
guessed that the newly upgraded Firefox didn’t work well with Linux
kernel 3.2.0-61, which was released on May 2 2014.  I forced the
machine to halt by pressing the power button for a while.  Then I
switched on the computer again, and chose “Memtest86+” in the GRUB
menu.  Within several minutes, the words in the blue screen blurred
due to some blinking dots.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="recalled-past-experience">Recalled past experience</h2>

<p>Half a year ago, I also encountered similar error in the RAM.  I paid
HKD$80 for a technician in a computer repair shop to check the
computer <em>without checking the hard disk</em>.  Unluckily, after leaving
the computer off for a few days, he couldn’t found any problem and
concluded that that was a “hard disk problem”.</p>

<p>As a result, I studied some commands for merging logical volumes in
different physical volumes into the <em>same</em> physical volume, so as to
use less space in my computer.</p>

<p>Thus, I planned to uninstall unnecessary packages the next day.</p>

<h2 id="development">Development</h2>

<p>This Sunday, I turned on my computer.  Quick as a flash, the power
button’s blue light changed to yellow, and the machine beeped.</p>

<h2 id="resolution">Resolution</h2>

<p>I searched “dell desktop beep”, and Google showed some related
searches.  I clicked on “dell desktop beep codes”, and found
<a href="http://support.dell.com/support/systemsinfo/document.aspx?~file=/systems/inspd530/en/om/html/trouble.htm#wp1085300">the official documentation on beep codes</a>.  Though it was
written for an older model in the same series, I believed that it
could be applied to my model as well.</p>

<p>To correctly identify the problem, I booted the faulty desktop again,
and heard four repetitive short beeps before a pause.  According to
the manual, the culprit was the RAM.</p>

<p>I could search for the suitable models of RAM for my desktop model,
but it took time and the Internet is not always a reliable source of
information.  If I buy the wrong RAM, I’ll have wasted several hundred
dollars.  Therefore, I decided to take my desktop to a computer repair
shop for replacing the RAM.</p>

<p>At noon, it was extremely hot, so I waited for a few hours and tried
<a href="/blog/2014/05/26/using-octopress-on-another-device/">setting up Octopress on my laptop</a>, which ran on
Windows 7 because I would like to write something about
<a href="/blog/2014/05/25/fixing-a-vim-error-caused-by-an-ultrablog-dot-vim-upgrade/">the recent Vim error caused by my outdated VIMRC</a>
before I forgot the cause and the solution of error.  I came across
some errors with long and complicated error messages. As a user but
<em>not</em> a developer, I couldn’t immediately figure out what happened.
Eventually, I spent a whole night to solve technical problems before I
started to write posts/pages hosted on the <em>same</em> blog in Vim on
<em>both</em> Ubuntu and Windows.  I will talk about that in greater detail
soon.</p>

<p>Ironically, in the afternoon, the technician took less than 30 minutes
to remove the old RAM and install the new one.</p>

<h2 id="lessons-learnt">Lessons learnt</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Stay calm when there’s a problem.</li>
  <li>GNU/Linux has utilities for finding out what’s going on inside my
  computer.</li>
  <li>Identify the true cause of the problem.</li>
  <li>Seek help from others if I can’t take the responsibility.</li>
  <li>Replacing a malfunctioning part of a computer is cheaper and more
  eco-friendly than buying a new computer.</li>
</ul>

<!-- vim:se tw=70: -->
]]></content>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Extend Laptop Lifespan]]></title>
      <link href="http://vincenttam.github.io/blog/2014/02/22/extend-notebook-lifespan/"/>
    
    <updated>2014-02-22T01:07:05+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://vincenttam.github.io/blog/2014/02/22/extend-notebook-lifespan</id>
    
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve found some useful pages about maintaining one’s notebook
computer.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.makeuseof.com/tag/5-laptop-maintenance-tips-to-extend-its-life-expectency/" title="A page on makeuseof">5 Laptop Maintenance Tips To Extend Its Life Expectancy</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://blogs.computerworld.com/20269/maximizing_the_lifespan_of_a_laptop_computer_battery" title="A page on Computerworld">Maximizing the lifespan of a laptop battery</a></li>
</ul>

<p>However, as a GNU/Linux user, I don’t think I need an anti-virus.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">

      <p><a href="http://www.howtogeek.com/135392/htg-explains-why-you-dont-need-an-antivirus-on-linux-and-when-you-do/" title="A page on How-To-Geek">HTG Explains: Why You Don’t Need an Antivirus On Linux (and When You Do)</a> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
